<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Project Atomic</title>
  <subtitle>Tag: Coreos</subtitle>
  <id>http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/</id>
  <link href="http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/"/>
  <link href="http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/tag/coreos.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Project Atomic. Sponsored by Red Hat, Inc.</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Announcing the Fedora CoreOS community!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/2018/06/welcome-to-fedora-coreos/"/>
    <id>http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/2018/06/welcome-to-fedora-coreos/</id>
    <published>2018-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-10-07T14:03:16+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dusty Mabe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Welcome to Fedora CoreOS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year Red Hat acquired &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/about/press-releases/red-hat-acquire-coreos-expanding-its-kubernetes-and-containers-leadership"&gt;CoreOS, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;.
In the past few
months we have been working hard to evaluate the different technologies 
in the CoreOS Container Linux and Project Atomic spaces. Since Container 
Linux and Atomic Host overlap in functionality quite a bit we have decided
to merge future development of the two projects so that we can combine
our efforts and bring two great communities of people together to solve
future challenges in the transactional update and container operating
system landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What does this mean for Atomic Host?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last major release of Fedora Atomic Host will most likely be Fedora
29 Atomic Host. After Fedora 29 we&amp;rsquo;ll recommend you use Fedora CoreOS for
any deployments. The use cases for Fedora CoreOS should overlap with the
existing use cases for Atomic Host, but there may be some use cases that
are left behind as we narrow our focus. Hopefully disruptions will be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What will happen to the Project Atomic community channels?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mailing lists, IRC channels, and GitHub organization will mostly
be retired once the last releases are End Of Life. Please join us on the
new community spaces (more details below)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Where can I learn more about Fedora CoreOS and get involved?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a new website and FAQ at &lt;a href="https://coreos.fedoraproject.org"&gt;https://coreos.fedoraproject.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a mailing list at &lt;a href="mailto:coreos@lists.fedoraproject.org"&gt;coreos@lists.fedoraproject.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an IRC channel #fedora-coreos on freenode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a new Discourse board at &lt;a href="https://discussion.fedoraproject.org/c/coreos"&gt;https://discussion.fedoraproject.org/c/coreos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For future blog posts around containers, please refer to the new website
that is currently under active development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to have the existing Container Linux and Atomic Host
communities working together and we hope you&amp;rsquo;ll join us in making
Fedora CoreOS a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
